Marie Paneth Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Marie Paneth Papers 1938-1968
MSS58735
Paneth, Marie
600 items
8 containers
2.8 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Artist, teacher, and writer. Correspondence, a diary, reports, notes, writings, and children’s artwork documenting Paneth’s therapeutic use of art in working with children who suffered traumatic experiences. Included is her work with children during the bombardment of London in 1941-1942 and her postwar work with children who survived German concentration camps.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Cizk, Franz.; Hartmann, Heinz, 1894-1970--Correspondence.; Paneth, Marie.
Subjects
Art.; Child Nazi concentration camp inmates.; Drawing.; Holocaust survivors.; World War, 1939-1945--Children--England--London.; World War, 1939-1945--Concentration camps.
Places
Austria--Social life and customs.; Indonesia--Social life and customs.; Vienna (Austria)--Social life and customs.
Occupations
Artists.; Authors.; Educators.
Provenance
The papers of Marie Paneth, artist, teacher, and writer, were given to the Library of Congress by the Sigmund Freud Archives between 1979 and 1985.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Marie Paneth are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Marie Paneth was born in Austria on August 15, 1895. She studied art with Franz Čižek whose theories on art education for children influenced her later work. Paneth was the daughter-in-law of Joseph Paneth, a friend of Sigmund Freud. She met Freud in 1920 shortly before moving to the Dutch East Indies with her husband. Paneth later moved to the United States, living and working in New York City where she exhibited with the Society of Independent Artists in 1939. She spent most of the war years in England where she worked as an art instructor with children traumatized by the bombing of London. After the war, she continued to explore the therapeutic uses of art among children who had survived German concentration camps. Paneth returned to New York in the early 1950s. She moved to France in the late 1960s and died in London in November 1986.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Marie Paneth (1895-1986) span the years 1938-1968 and include correspondence, a diary, reports, notes, writings, and children’s artwork. The collection documents Paneth’s therapeutic use of art in working with children who suffered traumatic experiences. Featured in the collection are writings based on her work with children during the bombardment of London in 1941-1942 and her postwar work with children who survived German concentration camps. Material in the collection is written in English and German.
The bulk of the collection consists of Paneth’s nonfiction and fiction writing. Included are fragments of drafts and reviews of her book, Branch Street. The book recounts her experiences as an art instructor in an air raid shelter in a poor section of London and explores the emotional lives of her pupils through their artwork. Paneth’s original reports outlining her work in the shelter are located in the subject file. Also included in the collection is an unpublished book-length manuscript entitled “Rock the Cradle” based on her subsequent work with children who survived internment in German concentration camps. The children arrived in England in 1945 and were housed in a former war workers’ hostel on Lake Windermere. Most of the children were over the age of fifteen. The largest number were born in Poland; others were from Czechoslovakia, Germany, and Hungary. Paneth’s manuscript relates stories told by the children about their experiences in concentration camps, their adjustment to life in the British reception camp, and the ways artwork provided a nonverbal outlet for their emotional trauma. A few examples of the children’s artwork is found in the subject file.
Other writings in the collection concern Paneth’s theories on the link between visual impressions expressed through drawing and the sensation and memory of eye movement. Also included are several works of fiction including short stories drawn from Paneth’s experiences as a doctor’s wife living in Java and Sumatra during the interwar years. An autobiographical novel entitled “Falschung,” written in English and German, recounts her childhood in Vienna, Austria, her art studies with Franz Čižek, and her early married life in the Dutch East Indies.
Paneth’s correspondence largely concerns her writing projects, most notably Branch Street. Also included are numerous letters to and from psychoanalyst Heinz Hartmann. A diary, spanning the years 1950-1955, documents Paneth’s early years in New York City following her immigration to the United States.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material and thereunder alphabetically by name of person, title of work, topic, or type of material. Formerly closed material is filed at the end.
Container List
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - General, 1939-1968, undated, (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - Hartmann, Heinz See Container 8, same heading (Box 1)
- Diary, 1951-1955 See also Container 8, same heading, (6 folders) (Box 1)
- Subject file (Box 2)
  - Children's artwork and related notes (Box 2)
    - "Lenny," 1956-1957 (Box 2)
    - "Leslie," undated (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
      - Drawings, 1946, undated (Box 2)
      - Notes, 1949-1951, undated (Box 2)
  - Society of Indpendent Artists exhibition, New York, N.Y., 1939 (Box 2)
  - Tilbury shelter ("Branch Street"), London, England, 1941-1942, undated (Box 2)
  - Windermere reception camp, Windermere, England, 1946-1948 (Box 2)
- Writings (Box 2)
  - Branch Street (Box 2)
    - Fragments of drafts, undated (Box 2)
    - Miscellany, 1942-1950, undated (Box 2)
    - Reviews, 1944-1950 (Box 2)
  - "The Eclipse," undated (Box 2)
  - "A European Deathbed," undated (Box 2)
  - "Falschung" ("Forgery") (Box 2)
    - In English, undated, (1 folder); (3 folders) (Box 2, Box 3)
    - In German, undated, (1 folder); (5 folders) (Box 3, Box 4)
  - "How to Finish War," 1938 (Box 5)
  - "Is Dying Easier There?" undated (Box 5)
  - "Japs in Sumatra," undated (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 5)
  - "No, I Am Here on a Visitor's Visa Only," undated (Box 5)
  - "Notes on Drawings and Paintings of Children from Concentration Camps," 1946 (Box 5)
  - "Notes Relating to the Phenomenon of Drawing," circa 1958-1964, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - "Observations Grouped Around the Functioning of Visual Memory," 1957 (Box 5)
  - "On Picture Making When Toddlers Begin to Draw," undated (Box 5)
  - "On Trauma and Motility," 1957 (Box 5)
  - "Rock the Cradle," circa 1947, (1 folder); (3 folders) (Box 5, Box 6)
  - "The Sacrifice," 1939, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - "Seven Nights," undated, (1 folder); (2 folders) (Box 6, Box 7)
  - "The Teen-Age[r] in the Office," undated (Box 7)
  - Unidentified notes and fragments, 1950, undated (Box 7)
- Formerly closed (Box 8)
  - Correspondence (Box 8)
    - Hartmann, Heinz (Box 8)
      - From Hartmann, 1938-1954, 1968 (Box 8)
      - To Hartmann, 1940-1956, 1964-1968, undated, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Diary, 1950-1954 See also Container 1, same heading (Box 8)